In the coming years, artificial intelligence
आने वाले सालों में आर्टिफिशल इंटेलिजेंस
is probably going to change your life, and likely the entire world.
शायद आपके जीवन,और संभवतः पूरी दुनिया को बदलने वाली है।
But people have a hard time agreeing on exactly how.
लेकिन कैसे - लोग इसपर सहमत नहीं हो पा रहे हैं।
The following are excerpts from a World Economic Forum interview
निम्नलिखित अंश वर्ल्ड इकोनॉमिक फ़ोरम के एक साक्षात्कार से हैं
where renowned computer science professor and AI expert Stuart Russell
जहाँ प्रख्यात कंप्यूटर विज्ञान प्रोफ़ेसर व ए-आई विशेषज्ञ स्टुअर्ट रसल
helps separate the sense from the nonsense.
समझदारी को बकवास से अलग करते हैं ।
There’s a big difference between asking a human to do something
एक मनुष्य को कुछ करने के लिए कहने में और उसे किसी ए-आई को उद्देश्य के रूप में
and giving that as the objective to an AI system.
देने में बहुत अंतर होता है।
When you ask a human to get you a cup of coffee,
जब आप किसी मनुष्य को एक कप कॉफ़ी लाने के लिए कहते हैं,
you don’t mean this should be their life’s mission,
इसका अर्थ यह नहीं कि वह उसके जीवन का उद्देश्य बन जाए,
and nothing else in the universe matters.
और दुनिया में कुछ भी मायने नहीं रखता
Even if they have to kill everybody else in Starbucks
चाहे उसके लिए उन्हें स्टारबक्स में हर किसी का
to get you the coffee before it closes— they should do that.
क़त्ल करना पड़े और दुकान बंद होने से पहले कॉफ़ी ले आएँ।
No, that’s not what you mean.
नहीं, आपका यह तात्पर्य नहीं है।
All the other things that we mutually care about,
हर वह चीज़ जिसके बारे में हम  साथ में सोचते हैं,
they should factor into your behavior as well.
उसका भी ध्यान रखना होगा।
And the problem with the way we build AI systems now
और अब हम जैसे ए-आई प्रणालियाँ बनाते हैं, उसकी समस्या यह है कि हम
is we give them a fixed objective.
उन्हें निश्चित उद्देश्य देते हैं।
The algorithms require us to specify everything in the objective.
हमें एल्गोरिथ्म में सब कुछ बताना पड़ता है।
And if you say, can we fix the acidification of the oceans?
और अगर आप कहें, क्या हम महासागरों के अम्लीकरण को ठीक कर सकते हैं ?
Yeah, you could have a catalytic reaction that does that extremely efficiently,
हाँ, आप कोई ऐसी प्रतिक्रिया बना सकते हैं जो यह बहुत कुशलतापूर्वक करती है,
but it consumes a quarter of the oxygen in the atmosphere,
लेकिन वह वायुमंडल की एक-चौथाई ऑक्सीजन का प्रयोग करती है,
which would apparently cause us to die fairly slowly and unpleasantly
जिसके कारण हम प्रकट रूप से कई घंटों के दौरान
over the course of several hours.
एक धीमी और दर्दनाक मौत मरेंगे।
So, how do we avoid this problem?
तो, हम इस समस्या को कैसे टाल सकते हैं ?
You might say, okay, well, just be more careful about specifying the objective—
आप शायद कहेंगे, ठीक है, उद्देश्य को स्पष्ट करते समय और ध्यान दें -
don’t forget the atmospheric oxygen.
वायुमंडल की ऑक्सीजन को न भूलें।
And then, of course, some side effect of the reaction in the ocean
और फिर, उस प्रतिक्रिया के किसी पार्श्व-प्रभाव के कारण
poisons all the fish.
सभी मछलियाँ मर जाती हैं।
Okay, well I meant don’t kill the fish either.
अच्छा, मछलियों को भी मत मारो।
And then, well, what about the seaweed?
और फिर समुद्री शैवालों का क्या ?
Don’t do anything that’s going to cause all the seaweed to die.
ऐसा कुछ मत करो जिससे समुद्री शैवाल मर जाएँ।
And on and on and on.
और वगैरह वगैरह वगैरह।
And the reason that we don’t have to do that with humans is that
और हमें यह मनुष्यों के साथ इसलिए नहीं करना पड़ता है क्योंकि
humans often know that they don’t know all the things that we care about.
मनुष्य अक्सर जानते हैं, वह हर चीज़ जो मायने रखती है, उसके बारे में नहीं पता होगा
If you ask a human to get you a cup of coffee,
अगर आप एक मनुष्य को एक कप कॉफ़ी लाने को कहते हैं
and you happen to be in the Hotel George Sand in Paris,
और आप पैरिस के होटल जॉर्ज सैंड में हैं,
where the coffee is 13 euros a cup,
जहाँ एक कप कॉफ़ी 13 यूरो का है,
it’s entirely reasonable to come back and say, well, it’s 13 euros,
यह बिलकुल वाजिब है कि वह आकर कहें, वह 13 यूरो का है,
are you sure you want it, or I could go next door and get one?
क्या आप वह लेना चाहते हैं, या मैं पड़ोस की दुकान से ले आऊँ ?
And it’s a perfectly normal thing for a person to do.
एक मनुष्य के लिए ऐसा करना बिलकुल सामान्य है
To ask, I’m going to repaint your house—
अगर वह पूछे, मैं आपका घर दोबारा रंगने वाला हूँ
is it okay if I take off the drainpipes and then put them back?
क्या मैं नाली की पाइप निकाल कर दोबारा लगा सकता हूँ ?
We don't think of this as a terribly sophisticated capability,
हम इसे कोई बहुत परिष्कृत क्षमता नहीं मानते हैं,
but AI systems don’t have it because the way we build them now,
लेकिन एआई में यह नहीं है क्योंकि हम अभी जैसे उन्हें बनाते हैं
they have to know the full objective.
उन्हें पूरा उद्देश्य पता होना चाहिए।
If we build systems that know that they don’t know what the objective is,
अगर हम ऐसी प्रणालियाँ बनाते हैं जिन्हें मालूम हो वे पूरा उद्देश्य नहीं जानतीं,
then they start to exhibit these behaviors,
तब वे ऐसा व्यव्हार दर्शाने लगते हैं,
like asking permission before getting rid of all the oxygen in the atmosphere.
जैसे वायुमंडल की सारी ऑक्सीजन हटाने से पहले अनुमति लेना।
In all these senses, control over the AI system
इन सभी मायनों में, ए-आई प्रणालियों पर नियंत्रण
comes from the machine’s uncertainty about what the true objective is.
मशीन की सच्चे उद्देश्य को लेकर अनिश्चितता से आता है।
And it’s when you build machines that believe with certainty
और जब आप ऐसी मशीनें बनाते हैं जो मानती हैं कि उनके पास
that they have the objective,
निश्चित उद्देश्य है,
that’s when you get this sort of psychopathic behavior.
तब आपको इस प्रकार की मनोरोगी प्रवृत्तियाँ दिखाई देती हैं।
And I think we see the same thing in humans.
और हम मनुष्यों में भी यही देखते हैं।
What happens when general purpose AI hits the real economy?
क्या होता है जब सामान्य उद्देश्य वाला ए-आई असली अर्थव्यवस्था में प्रवेश करता है ?
How do things change? Can we adapt?
चीज़ें कैसे बदलती हैं? क्या हम अपने आप को ढाल सकते हैं ?
This is a very old point.
यह एक बहुत पुरानी बात है।
Amazingly, Aristotle actually has a passage where he says,
आश्चर्य से, अरिस्टोटल एक गद्यांश में कहते हैं,
look, if we had fully automated weaving machines
देखिये, अगर हमारे पास पूर्णतः स्वचालित बुनाई की मशीन होती
and plectrums that could pluck the lyre and produce music without any humans,
और मिज़राब जो स्वयं वाद्ययंत्र के तार छेड़ बिना मनुष्य के संगीत उत्पन्न कर सकें,
then we wouldn’t need any workers.
तो हमें कारीगरों की कोई ज़रुरत नहीं होगी।
That idea, which I think it was Keynes
यह विचार, जिसे मुझे लगता है केन्ज़ ने
who called it technological unemployment in 1930,
1930 में तकनीकी बेरोज़गार बुलाया था,
is very obvious to people.
लोगों में काफ़ी स्पष्ट है।
They think, yeah, of course, if the machine does the work,
वे सोचते हैं, हाँ, बेशक, अगर मशीन काम करेगी,
then I'm going to be unemployed.
तो मैं बेरोज़गार हो जाऊँगा।
You can think about the warehouses that companies are currently operating
ऑनलाइन खरीदारी के लिए कंपनियों के गोदामों के बारे में सोचें
for e-commerce, they are half automated.
वे आधे स्वचालित हैं।
The way it works is that an old warehouse— where you’ve got tons of stuff piled up
यह ऐसे काम करता है कि एक पुराना गोदाम - जहाँ इधर-उधर बहुत सारा सामान एकत्रित है
all over the place and humans go and rummage around
और इंसान जाकर, भाग-दौड़ करके, पूरा गोदाम छान मारके
and then bring it back and send it off—
और उसे वापस लाकर भेज देते हैं -
there’s a robot who goes and gets the shelving unit
एक रोबोट है जो जाकर वह पूरा दराज ही उठा लाए
that contains the thing that you need,
जिसमें जो सामान चाहिए, रखा है,
but the human has to pick the object out of the bin or off the shelf,
लेकिन इंसान को डब्बे या दराज में से वह सामान उठाना है,
because that’s still too difficult.
क्योंकि वह फिर भी कठिन है।
But, at the same time,
लकिन, उसी समय,
would you make a robot that is accurate enough to be able to pick
क्या आप एक ऐसा रोबोट बनाएंगे जो इतना सही हो कि
pretty much any object within a very wide variety of objects that you can buy?
सारी वस्तुओं में से लगभग कोई भी वस्तु उठा सके ?
That would, at a stroke, eliminate 3 or 4 million jobs?
वह एक ही बार में 30 या 40 लाख नौकरियाँ ख़त्म कर देगा ?
There's an interesting story that E.M. Forster wrote,
ई एम् फ़ॉस्टर ने एक दिलचस्प कहानी लिखी है
where everyone is entirely machine dependent.
जिसमें सब पूरी तरह मशीनों पर निर्भर हैं।
The story is really about the fact that if you hand over
यह कहानी इस बारे में है कि अगर आप सभ्यता का प्रबंधन
the management of your civilization to machines,
मशीनों के हाथ में डाल देते हैं,
you then lose the incentive to understand it yourself
तब आप उसे स्वयं समझने का या अगली पीढ़ी को समझाने का
or to teach the next generation how to understand it.
प्रोत्साहन खो देते हैं।
You can see “WALL-E” actually as a modern version,
आप वॉल-ई को एक आधुनिक संस्करण समझ सकते हैं
where everyone is enfeebled and infantilized by the machine,
जहाँ सब मशीनों के कारण अक्षम बन गए हैं,
and that hasn’t been possible up to now.
और यह अब तक संभव नहीं हो सका है।
We put a lot of our civilization into books,
हम अपनी सभ्यता को किताबों में डाल देते हैं,
but the books can’t run it for us.
पर किताबें सभ्यता नहीं चला सकतीं।
And so we always have to teach the next generation.
तो हमें अगली पीढ़ी को हमेशा ही सिखाना पड़ता है।
If you work it out, it’s about a trillion person years of teaching and learning
अगर हम इसे समझ लें, यह अरबों सालों की शिक्षा है
and an unbroken chain that goes back tens of thousands of generations.
और एक अटूट श्रृंखला जो दस हज़ारों पीढ़ियों से चली आ रही है।
What happens if that chain breaks?
क्या होगा अगर यह श्रृंखला टूट जाती है ?
I think that’s something we have to understand as AI moves forward.
मुझे लगता है हमें यह समझना होगा जैसे ए आई प्रगति करता है।
The actual date of arrival of general purpose AI—
सामान्य ए आई की आने की तारीख -
you’re not going to be able to pinpoint, it isn’t a single day.
आप नहीं बता सकते हैं - यह कोई एक दिन नहीं है।
It’s also not the case that it’s all or nothing.
और यह ′या सब कुछ, या कुछ नहीं′ - ऐसा भी नहीं है।
The impact is going to be increasing.
इसका प्रभाव तो बढ़ेगा।
So with every advance in AI,
तो ए आई की हर उन्नति के साथ,
it significantly expands the range of tasks.
कार्यक्षमता की श्रेणी भी काफ़ी हद तक बढ़ जाती है।
So in that sense, I think most experts say by the end of the century,
तो उस मायने में, मैं सोचता हूँ, ज़्यादातर विशेषज्ञ कहते हैं कि सदी एक अंत तक
we’re very, very likely to have general purpose AI.
सामान्य ए आई के आने की बहुत संभावना है।
The median is something around 2045.
माध्यक 2045 के आस-पास है।
I'm a little more on the conservative side.
मैं थोड़ा रूढ़िवादी हूँ।
I think the problem is harder than we think.
मुझे लगता है यह हमारी समझ से कठिन है।
I like what John McAfee, he was one of the founders of AI,
मुझे पसंद है जॉन मक-अफ़ी, जो ए आई के एक प्रवर्तक हैं,
when he was asked this question, he said, somewhere between five and 500 years.
जब उनसे यह सवाल पूछा गया, उन्होंने कहा - पाँच से 500 साल के बीच।
And we're going to need, I think, several Einsteins to make it happen.
और मुझे लगता है, ऐसा करने के लिए आइंस्टीन जैसे कई सारे विद्वान लगेंगे।